Finding Aid for Marjorie Lansing Papers, 1937-1998
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Marjorie Lansing Papers 1937-1998 1967-1993
Lansing, Marjorie
.5 linear feet
Political science professor at Eastern Michigan University, 1965-1986, known for research on "gender gap" in voting behavior, active in Washtenaw County Democratic party. Records document her research and teaching activities.
98120 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was received from John Stephen Lansing and Carol Lansing in August 1998. Donor no. 4976
The collection is open for research.
Marjorie Lansing was known for her research on the "gender gap" in voting behavior, political activism, and enthusiastic teaching style in political science. She was born on April 2, 1916 in Geneva, Florida. She received a bachelor's degree from the Florida State College for Women in 1937 and a master's degree in sociology from Columbia University in 1941. Between 1941 and 1945, she worked in Washington D.C. as a research investigator. She married John Lansing in 1945 and moved to Cambridge, Massachusetts, where he finished his Ph.D. at Harvard. In 1949, they moved to Ann Arbor, Michigan, where he was a professor of economics at the University of Michigan from 1949 to 1970 and program director of the Institute for Social Research. In this time, Marjorie Lansing raised three children and volunteered actively for the Democratic Party in Washtenaw County. She was elected as delegate to the Democratic National Convention in 1960 and 1976. She served as president of the Ann Arbor Democratic Women's Club for two years, chaired the Ann Arbor Township Democratic Committee for five years, and was precinct delegate to county and state conventions for twelve years.
Lansing began graduate study at the University of Michigan in political science in 1961 and received her Ph.D. in 1970. She was hired as a part-time lecturer at Eastern Michigan University in 1965, was promoted to full-time in 1968, and became a full professor in 1977. Throughout her career, she expanded her dissertation topic about women's political behavior and status into books, numerous articles, and conference papers. She co-authored her two most important works with Sandra Baxter: Women and Politics: The Invisible Majority in 1980 and Women and Politics: The Visible Majority in 1983. Amidst teaching and research, she ran for the University of Michigan Board of Regents in 1972 and 1984 and for Congress in 1974. She also remained active in local political associations and research communities for women's studies and political science. For example, she served as president of the Women's Caucus of the Midwest Political Science Association in 1982-1983. She was selected as a member of the Executive Committee of the Michigan Women Studies Association in 1985. She also was a member of the International Advisory Board of the Third Interdisciplinary Congress on Women in 1987. In 1986, she retired from Eastern Michigan University, but later accepted a visiting professorship at the University of Southern California in 1990-1991. She died in 1998.
The collection is divided into two series: Biographical and Research and Teaching.
The Marjorie Lansing Papers document the personal, professional, and political activities of Marjorie Lansing (1916-1998), who was an Eastern Michigan University Professor of Political Science, University of Michigan alumna, and feminist political activist. The collection contains material from 1937 to 1998, with a concentration from 1967 to 1993. It provides insights into her career, political viewpoints, research agenda, and others' perceptions of her.
Subjects:
Lansing, Marjorie, 1916-; Voting Research.; Gender Differences.; Women in Politics -- Michigan.; Women College Teachers -- Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Lansing, Marjorie, 1916-; Political Elections -- Michigan.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Portrait Photographs.; Portrait Drawings.
- Biographical
  The Biographical series contains ten folders and is organized alphabetically. The series includes information about her life and her personal records. The Biographical Sketches and Vitae Folder contains three different versions of her vita, an autobiographical narrative, and her obituary. There is also a folder of photographic portraits from different periods in her life. Two folders of newspaper clippings provide information about her political campaigns, viewpoints, and research activities. Publicity for her three political campaigns and informal birthday tributes provide significant information about her life and personality.
  - Awards (Box 1)
  - Biographical sketches and vitae (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1992 (Box 1)
  - Family vacation from London to Bombay, 1967-1968, (includes 15 photographs) (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings
    - undated, 1971-1980 (Box 1)
    - 1982-1988 (Box 1)
  - Photographic and penciled portraits (Box 1)
  - Political campaigns (Box 1)
  - Recommendations and tributes (Box 1)
- Research and Teaching
  The Research and Teaching series contains six folders and is organized alphabetically. The series includes Lansing's writings and other material from her academic career. It contains unpublished papers and speeches as well as an incomplete third revision to her book, renamed Women and Politics: The Puzzling Majority. The series also includes advertisements and descriptions of public lectures, conferences, and classes. The "Distinguished Faculty Award Nomination: Research and Publication" document contains assessments of her contribution to political science and Eastern Michigan University, book reviews, and professional and student recommendations.
  - Classes (Box 1)
  - Conferences and lectures (Box 1)
  - "Distinguished Faculty Award Nomination: Research and Publication", 1985 (Box 1)
  - Papers (Box 1)
  - Unfinished manuscripts, 2 folders; (fragmentary) (Box 1)